Lord Aldarp is going to have a wedding.
阿尔达普大人要举行婚礼了
What a joyous occasion.
可喜可贺
-Aldarp -The lady over there and thee little boy,
-阿尔达普那家伙 -那边的小姐
-might be getting impatient. -take one too.
-可能是等不及了 -和小男孩也拿吧
Skipped various steps
跳过各种步骤
and set the wedding date.
决定好婚礼的日期了
Kazuma, this isn't the time to fight.
和真 现在是闹别扭的时候吗
She said this was her decision, right?
她说过这是她的决定吧
Before she apologizes to me in tears,
在她哭着来跟我道歉之前
I won't do anything.
我什么都不会做的
I won't agree to this.
我是不会认同的
If you go on like this to the big day,
要是就这样迎接当天
I'll have my own plans.
我也有自己的打算
Hey, don't do anything dangerous.
喂 你可别想些危险的事哦
Alright, give that back to me.
好了 把那个还给我
I've been working on it all morning.
我从早就开始做 好不容易才做到那个程度
What is this?
这是什么啊
It's for popping.
用来捏爆的
Pop them one by one.
一个一个捏爆
It's an entertainment
透过捏爆它来玩
to keep you relaxed.
让心情保持平静的东西
Is that it?
就这样吗
That's it.
就这样
(Konosuba S3)
《为美好的世界献上祝福！ 第三季》
Hello?
请问…
(Episode 10: Wishes for the Stubborn Bride) I have come here
(第10集 为任性的新娘献上祝福) 我今天是有事
to consult with Mr. Kazuma.
来找和真先生商量的
Has Darkness finally given in?
难道是达克妮丝让步
She's asking for my help…?
来求我帮忙…吗
To the Dustiness family.
通知达斯堤尼斯家
I've received news through connections
我从某个管道收到消息
that a senior member of the Devil King's Army
说近期魔王军的一位干部
will carry out a terrorist attack
将会在阿克塞尔的艾莉丝教会
at Axel's Eris Order.
发动恐怖攻击
The attack is scheduled on the wedding day.
恐怖攻击的日期就是婚礼当天
If the wedding is not canceled immediately,
如果不立刻取消婚礼
the church will be blown away by Explosion on that day.
婚礼当天教会就会被爆裂魔法炸飞
I hope you will heed my advice.
希望你们接受我的劝告
With kind regards, the magician.
亲切的魔法师敬上
I am very sorry!
非常抱歉
I will give that idiot a good scolding!
我会好好责骂那个笨蛋的
(Konosuba) Megumin!
惠惠
I have something to say to you. Come out!
我有话要跟你说 给我出来
The days without Darkness passed by just like that.
达克妮丝不在的时光 就这样一直流逝
I've decided to leave it be.
我决定放着不管
As for the two of them…
至于她们两个…
Look, out of this tiny pouch,
请看 从这个小小的包里
a Beginner's Bane will emerge.
会冒出初学者杀手哦
Don't let it out!
别让那种东西冒出来啦
Hey, what are you doing?
喂 你做什么啊
Let me go.
放开我
So many people are gathered here
这么多人聚集在这里
to watch my performance!
就为了看我表演耶
That's why I was called here.
所以我才会被叫来
What you're doing at someone else's doorstep
你在别人家门口做这种事
is causing them a lot of trouble.
让他们很困扰
-I was told to stop you. -Let me go!
-叫我来阻止你 -放开我
-Hey, show us! -Everyone is waiting.
-喂 快让我们看 -大家都在等着
-Yeah. -Show us!
-对啊对啊 -快让我们看
Please don't tip.
请不要打赏
Because I am not a performer.
因为我并不是艺人
Kazuma.
和真
What?
怎样啦
It's a strategy to lure Darkness out of her home.
这是把达克妮丝 从家里引出来的策略
What?
什么
Exactly.
没错
Don't you know the story of Amano-Iwato?
你不知道天岩户的故事吗
Yes, that's it.
就是那个
Hey! Darkness, do you hear me?
喂 达克妮丝 你有听到吧
Come out quickly!
快点出来
Come!
来吧
You'll regret it if you don't come closer to watch.
不靠近一点看会后悔的哦
I'm going to perform my best act.
我现在要表演拿手好戏
Hey, Kazuma!
等一下 和真
What are you doing? Let me go!
你在做什么 放开我
It's enough, we're going back.
够了 快点回去吧
No!
我不要
Before Darkness comes out,
在达克妮丝出来之前
I will perform here every day.
我每天都会来这里表演的
Hey, Darkness!
喂 达克妮丝
Darkness!
达克妮丝
A few days later.
接着几天后
I'm back.
我回来了
Has it been three days already?
已经过了三天了吗
I told you, didn't I?
我说过了吧
You'll get arrested for sending threatening letters.
寄恐吓信给别人会被抓的
You better behave.
你给我安分一点哦
Up to now, you and Aqua
到目前为止 你和阿库娅
have only been causing trouble for the Dustiness family.
只是一直在给达斯堤尼斯家添麻烦
Kazuma, it's about time you help out.
和真 你也差不多该帮忙了吧
If Darkness asks me, I'll help.
达克妮丝来求我 我就帮
How cold-blooded.
冷血的家伙
The people in town call you scum or trash.
镇上的人都叫你人渣真或垃圾真
I thought no matter what they said,
我本来以为不管别人说什么
you wouldn't abandon a friend in trouble
你都不会丢下有难的伙伴不管
and would step up at critical times.
是该出面的时候就会出面的人
At times like this, the one I love
我喜欢的人在这种时候
would look annoyed
虽然会一脸不耐烦抱怨
and complain,
说什么"真拿你没办法"
but he would still help me.
但还是会帮我
That's the kind of person he is.
他就是这样的人
If you think this vague confession
你以为含糊地说喜欢我
will make me help you,
我就会帮你
you're greatly mistaken.
那就大错特错了
I'm not so easily fooled.
我可没有那么好骗
Stop!
住手 住手
And finally,
接着终于
the day of Darkness' wedding came.
来到达克妮丝举行婚礼的当天
Let's go, Kazuma.
和真 走咯
Let's ruin the wedding.
我们一起毁掉婚礼吧
Magic can accidentally destroy the venue
魔法不小心射偏摧毁了会场
or the lord's house.
或魔法不小心射偏摧毁了领主家
It happens all the time.
都是常有的事
Hey, don't do that.
喂 别那么做
I mean it.
我是说真的
Not only will we end up in debt again,
别说又会欠债了
but this can make us criminals.
这次还会变成真正的罪犯
You'll regret it if you don't go.
不去的话会后悔的
I won't go.
我不去
What?
什么
You don't care about that lord
你不在乎那个领主
doing whatever he wants to Darkness?
对达克妮丝为所欲为吗
Do you really not care?
你真的无所谓吗
Of course I care!
怎么可能无所谓
Of course I care.
怎么可能无所谓…
You may not know
你可能不知道
that the man will stop at nothing
那个大叔会不择手段
to possess the women he desires.
把自己看上的好女人占为己有
After he grows tired of them,
而且玩腻之后
he discards them with a small alimony.
就付很少的赡养费抛弃对方
What's worse,
更恶劣的是
despite his despicable behavior,
他明明像这样为所欲为
we just can't find the crucial evidence for some reason.
不知道为什么 就是找不到关键性的证据
His reputation is terrible.
风评非常差
Then we should go.
那就更应该去
If you go,
如果是你
you should be able to come up with some ideas.
应该能想到什么鬼点子吧
This time, I'm powerless.
这次我实在无能为力
It's a wedding between nobles.
这是贵族之间的婚礼
The security is strict.
戒备很森严
No matter what we do,
事到如今不管做什么
we can't get close to them.
我们都无法接近他们
Rather, this is precisely why
不如说正是因为这样
I've been waiting for Darkness to ask me for help.
之前我才会一直 等达克妮丝向我求救
Kazuma.
和真…
Darkness' father is seriously ill.
达克妮丝的父亲生了重病
And I have no noble connections who could introduce me.
也没有其他能帮我引荐的贵族人脉
After all, I'm just an insignificant adventurer.
毕竟我只是微不足道的冒险者
This is what they call a disparity in social status.
这就是人家说的身份地位悬殊
Besides,
再说了
Darkness and we live in different worlds.
我们和达克妮丝 明明住在不同的世界
That we've managed to go on adventures together up till now
却能一起冒险到现在
is in itself a miracle.
简直就是奇迹
Now I know
我现在知道
you're also trying to help her.
你也在想办法帮她了
For me, that's enough.
对我来说 这样就够了
I will figure out a way by myself.
我会自己想办法
I'll embark on a path I won't regret.
踏上不会后悔那条路
I hope you'll give it some thought
希望你也好好想想
and then set out on a path you won't regret.
然后踏上不会后悔的那条路
I'm going.
我走了
What can I do with her?
真拿她没办法
Hi, hello!
嗨 你好
Leave your unreliable partners.
丢下不可靠的伙伴
A clairvoyant demon came to your rescue.
能够预知的恶魔来帮忙了
Vanir?
巴尼尔
Weep with joy at my arrival.
为我的登场喜极而泣
Cheer with all your might.
手舞足蹈就好
Come,
来吧
let me see all your intellectual properties.
让我看看你拥有的各种知识吧
What?
什么
Why must I do business with you
为什么在这种意志消沉的时候
when I'm so dispirited?
我还得跟你谈生意啊
Bring the beautiful lady manager.
换美女店长过来 换人
That debt-generating machine
那个负债制造机
can't possibly do business properly.
怎么可能好好谈生意
Yesterday, when I wasn't paying attention,
她昨天也趁我不注意的时候
'This can be sold to adventurer couple,' she said,
说"这可以卖给情侣冒险者"
and purchased this necklace.
进了这个项链
What is that?
那是什么
When the one wearing this suffers a fatal injury,
带着这个的人受到命危的重伤
it'll catch fire and explode right before they die.
就会在临死前起火爆炸的项链
The concept
概念是…
is to sacrifice one's life
在最后一刻牺牲生命
to protect someone important.
守护重要的人
Isn't that romantic?
不觉得很浪漫吗
She said this with a smile.
她高兴地笑着这么说
But its power is too strong.
但是它的威力太强了
Not to mention the enemy,
别说敌人了
even the one who should have been protected
连原本应该保护的心爱对象
will be blasted away.
都会被炸飞
This is an item that makes one question
是让人怀疑店主做生意的脑袋
the store owner's intelligence.
是不是有问题的东西
Do you want this?
你要拿一个吗
Nope.
我不要
Right, what do you mean you came to my rescue?
比起这个 你说来帮我是什么意思
It seems you've followed my advice
看来你按照我的建言
and have been working hard on products.
很努力开发商品呢
Therefore…
所以
These… are my intellectual properties.
这…这些是我剩下的知识成果
I have no intention of selling them cheap.
我可不打算便宜卖哦
You want to save her,
明明很想去救她
yet you fear being rejected by the girl in armor
却害怕去了之后
if you go there.
会被穿盔甲的女孩拒绝的男人啊
The demon Vanir hereby declares
能够预知的恶魔巴尼尔在此宣布
to purchase all of your intellectual property rights.
用你所有的知识产权做交换
The money in this bag
这个包里的钱
will certainly fulfill your wishes.
一定能达成你的愿望
Then let me confirm
那就让我确认一下
all your properties and rights.
你所有的知识和权利吧
Vanir,
我说巴尼尔
you can know many things, right?
你能知道很多事吧
Hm.
嗯
I can foresee most things.
大部分的事我都能预知
For example, the question you want to ask.
例如你接下来想问的问题
Of course, I also know
我当然也知道
why the girl in armor
那个穿盔甲的女孩
owes the lord a huge debt,
为什么会欠领主庞大的债务
and why no evidence can be found
为什么那个领主
after that lord
做了那么多坏事
have done so many evil things.
却找不到任何证据呢
Hey.
我问你
-You are a demon… -A demon,
-你明明是恶魔… -明明是恶魔
yet why so eager to help?
为什么要积极帮忙
Is there some ulterior motive?
难道有什么企图吗
Of course, there is.
当然有企图啦
After all, I am a demon.
毕竟我可是恶魔嘛
However, this time our interests align.
不过这次我和你的利害关系一致
That's why I would help you.
所以才会帮你
For instance, I could take this chance
比方说 我能趁这个机会
to have you sell all sorts of rights
要你把为了以备不时之需
you have hidden away for emergencies
藏起来的各种权利
at a cheap price.
通通便宜卖给我
The clairvoyant Mr. Demon.
能够预知的恶魔先生
You're a tough opponent.
真的很棘手呢
So,
话说回来
since you know my questions,
既然你知道我要问什么
then you might as well just tell me.
那就别卖关子快告诉我
Alright, alright.
好吧 好吧
I'll tell you.
那我就告诉你吧
Sacred Exorcism!
Sacred Exorcism
Wait!
等等
Aren't you a powerful demon?
你不是厉害的恶魔吗
You couldn't possibly be defeated by the Goddess of Toilets!
不可能因为厕所女神的攻击 就完蛋吧
What?
什么
I was away for a little bit.
我只是稍微没注意
Why have you become a demon's friend?
为什么你就变成恶魔的伙伴啊
And besides, I am the Goddess of Water.
而且我是水之女神才对
You always meddle.
每次都多管闲事
Never to be seen when you're needed.
之前明明不见人影
I went to receive guests.
我去接待客人啦
What guest?
客人是谁啊
The steward… Sir?
管家…先生?
You seem to be busy.
您好像正在忙
Then I will take my leave.
那我先告辞了
No, this is…
不 这是…
Daring to ambush me? How bold.
竟敢偷袭我 胆子真大
Rogue goddess.
流氓女神
Look.
你看
My handsome mask is cracked.
我帅气的面具都裂开了
Shut it.
讨厌啦
Do I have to declare in advance
难道每次驱逐害虫的时候
every time I expel pests?
我都要事先声明我现在要驱逐你咯
Are you stupid?
你傻了吗
Pfft pfft.
噗噗噗噗
(Konosuba) Hey, stop interfering with us.
喂 够了 别妨碍我们
Alright, the man with the goddess by his side
好了 虽然女神就在身边
yet cannot rely on her.
却无法依靠女神的可怜男人啊
What you want to know is
你想知道的是
why the girl in armor is in debt, right?
那个穿盔甲的女孩为什么会欠债吧
Right.
对
The cause of this
这件事的起因
is that you adventurers
是因为你们这些冒险者
defeated the Mobile Fortress Destroyer.
打倒了机动要塞毁灭者
Destroyer?
毁灭者?
Do explain.
说得详细点
Generally speaking, when the Destroyer appears,
一般来说 毁灭者出现的时候
Lords will lose their land.
领主会失去土地
However,
但是这座城市
with your desperate efforts,
在你们的拼命努力之下
this city did not come to that.
没有变成那样
Isn't that a good thing?
这不是好事吗
The town itself was saved.
城镇本身是得救了
Yes, I mean the town itself.
没错 我是说城镇本身
But the granary areas along the way
可是途中的谷仓地带
were ravaged by all sorts of things.
却被各种各样的东西摧残
Those farmers
以务农维生的人们
have practically lost everything.
可以说是失去一切
So they ran to the lord for help.
因此农民跑来找领主求救
Yes, as you expected,
没错 跟你预料的一样
this is what the lord said.
那个领主这么说
You should be grateful that you're still alive.
能保住一条命就算赚到了吧
Even if left unattended, weeds will still grow.
就算放着不管 还是长得出杂草吧
Like that.
像这样
It's impossible to describe it as a natural disaster
告诉人们这就像天灾一样
and have the people give up.
要他们放弃是不可能的吧
They cried and pleaded,
人们哭着哀求
yes,
没错
to the Dustiness family
就是向与你关系深厚的
who you know well.
达斯堤尼斯家族
This is what those people said.
那些人这么说了
The adventurers compensated
冒险者们赔偿了
for the buildings destroyed by the flood.
被洪水冲毁的建筑物损失
The benevolent Lady Dustiness,
仁慈的达斯堤尼斯大人
please pity us too.
也请您怜悯我们吧
Like this.
像这样
What did you just say?
你刚刚说什么
About the buildings destroyed by the flood.
被洪水冲毁的建筑物怎么了
When they requested compensation from you,
对方要求你赔偿的时候
they said
不是这么说了吗
'I won't ask for full compensation,'
"我不会要你们全额赔偿"
'but please compensate at least a part.'
"请你们至少赔偿一部分"
The Dustiness family
达斯堤尼斯家
lost more than half of their property
为了弥补之前洪水造成的损害
to compensate for the damage.
失去了一大半财产
And that's not all.
还不只这样
To help those ravaged by the Destroyer,
为了帮助被毁灭者摧残的人们
they went to borrow money from the lord
他们去拜托放弃责任的领主
who disclaimed responsibility.
向他借钱
The lord proposed an attached condition.
对方提出这样的附带条件
If you don't have money,
如果还不出钱来
repay me with your body.
就用你的身体抵押偿还吧
Kazuma.
我说和真
Pounding the table must hurt.
生气捶桌子一定很痛吧
It hurts, doesn't it?
很痛吧
Then everything makes sense.
这样一切就说得通了
How much money does Darkness owe?
达克妮丝欠了多少钱
The property you own
客人你拥有的财产
plus the money in this bag
和这个包里的钱加起来
amounts exactly to the debt.
正好就是债款的金额
So, let's talk business.
那么 我们来谈生意吧
Miss, you are very beautiful.
大小姐 您非常美哦
After the wedding,
婚礼结束后
please let the sick master
也请您让卧病在家的老爷
take a look at you.
看看这个模样吧
Get lost!
滚开
Lalatina is about to become mine anyway.
反正拉拉蒂娜就要成为我的人了
Only people from the Dustiness House can pass through here.
只有达斯堤尼斯家的人能通过这里
Please go back.
您请回吧
You fool!
说什么蠢话
Listen.
听好了
After the wedding,
婚礼结束后
I will become your master.
你的主人就变成我了
I cannot let you pass.
我不能让您通过
You are not my master yet.
您还不是我的主人
Wha…
什…
I'll remember your face.
我记住你的脸了
Just you wait after the wedding.
婚礼结束后给我走着瞧
Can you ask the person outside to come in?
能不能叫门外的人进来
I want to thank him.
我想跟他道谢
Yes.
是
Please.
请进
Well, well.
真令人惊讶
You are very beautiful.
您非常美丽
I'm sorry.
对不起
I will talk to him.
我会跟那个人说
You will not be punished.
绝对不会让你受到惩罚
Please don't mind.
请您不用在意
Since he is approved by the young lady,
既然是大小姐认同的男人
I am willing to serve him.
属下也愿意服侍他
I approved, huh?
认同的男人吗…
Seeing your smile
最后能看到您露出笑容
makes me feel very happy, young lady.
属下觉得很幸福
It might be a bit presumptuous.
这么说也许有点僭越
You are so beautiful.
您这么美丽
It's better not to play intense games alone.
还是别独自玩激烈的游戏比较好
Darn it.
真是的
It's all that man's fault for imitating my voice.
都怪那个男人没事模仿我的声音
A person born as a noble
本来 生为贵族的人
does not have the right
就无法按照自己的意思
to live as they please.
随心所欲过活
Despite this,
尽管如此
I am fortunate to have lived up till now
我却有幸能和推心置腹的伙伴
with friends I can trust.
一起生活到现在
It's enough.
已经足够了
To desire more would be greedy.
再渴望更多就太奢侈了
Now it's my turn to repay everyone in the town.
这次轮到我报答镇上的大家了
Young lady?
大小姐?
Sorry.
抱歉
I'm fine.
我没事
What will they think once they know the reason for my debt?
大家知道我欠债的原因后 会怎么想呢
Megumin will probably get angry.
惠惠应该会发脾气
Aqua might burst into tears.
阿库娅可能会莫名其妙哭出来
As for him,
至于那家伙
he'll likely lecture me
应该会教训我
that I've done a stupid thing.
为什么要做这种蠢事
Precisely the last thing I want him to do.
精准料中我最不希望他做的事
Carry it out then.
迅速去执行吧
Will he come?
他会来吗
No, he won't come.
不 一定不会来吧
Given his personality,
依他的个性
he's definitely sulking
肯定在呕气
alone at home.
自己一个人关在家里吧
It's time, young lady.
时间到了 大小姐
The priest blessing you today
今天要祝福你们的祭司
is the most influential person in town.
是镇上最有影响力的人
This wedding will be great.
这场婚礼一定会很棒
I'm so happy.
好开心啊
This year I spent with them,
和大家一起度过的这一年
I was so cheerful every day.
每天都好快乐
So happy.
好幸福
Don't push.
别推挤 别推挤
Can't see inside at all.
完全看不到里面
I wish you all the happiness, young lady.
祝大小姐过得幸福
Bride Darkness
新娘达克妮丝
is soon to marry this guy who looks like a bear and pig combined.
即将嫁给这个 长得像熊和猪合体的大叔
She follows a fate not decided by me, a goddess,
遵从不是我这个神决定的命运
and becomes his wife.
随波逐流和他成为夫妻
Do you swear that in health
你发誓无论健康的时候
or sickness,
生病的时候
in happiness
开心的时候
or sadness,
难过的时候
in wealth
富有的时候
or poverty,
贫穷的时候
you will love this old man,
都会爱着大叔
respect him,
尊敬大叔
comfort him,
安慰大叔
help him,
帮助大叔
and be loyal to him for this life?
一生一世 坚守自己的贞操吗
Calling me an old man?
大叔…
You can't do it, can you?
一定办不到吧
Darkness, I want to go back with you,
我想就这样和达克妮丝一起回去
eat the food made by Kazuma,
吃着和真做的料理
and then have a drink.
然后爽快地喝一杯
You… you're the woman who came to my house
你…你是之前来我家
and caused me a lot of trouble!
给我添了一堆麻烦的女人
Dad, mom.
爸爸 妈妈
You've always taught your darling son
你们一直教育可爱的儿子
to be an upright person.
要当一个正直的人
-I no longer know what a mundane life is. -Go, Kazuma! Show him what you've got.
-我已经不知道平凡的人生在哪 -上啊 和真 给他好看
-I'm getting ready to fight the most powerful person in the area -Go! Kazuma!
-正打算对抗当地最有权力的人 -GOGO 耶 和真
-and kidnap a noble young lady. -Go! Show him!
-绑架贵族的大小姐 -上啊 给他好看 耶
Let's go home, Darkness!
回去了 达克妮丝
(Episode 11: Blessings for the Unchanging Daily Life)
(第11集 为不变的日常献上祝福)
Lord Demon King.
魔王大人
We…
我们
are living on the beautiful Sanzu River.
正在美好的三途川过生活
We will keep enjoying it to the fullest.
今后我们也会尽情享受…